Warning

Do not abruptly stop most psychiatric drugs!

Most psychiatric drugs are far more dangerous to take than people realize, but they also can become dangerous when discontinued too abruptly. As described in this book, most have addictive qualities and can produce withdrawal symptoms that are emotionally and physically distressing and sometimes life-threatening. Drugs that can produce withdrawal symptoms include neuroleptics or antipsychotics, such as Haldol or Thorazine; antidepressants, such as Tofranil and Elavil; stimulants, such as Ritalin; minor tranquilizers, such as Valium and Xanax; and prescription sedatives or sleeping pills.

Stopping psychiatric drugs should usually be done gradually, and only with professional guidance.

No book can substitute for individualized medical or psychological care. However, it is important to find help consistent with one’s own philosophy. The aim of this book is to present a psychosocial viewpoint. It cannot be used as a treatment handbook.

Introduction

What Is Psychiatry?

Many people don’t know the difference between psychiatry, psychotherapy, psychology, and psychoanalysis. This book is primarily about psychiatry—a specialty within the field of medicine. Psychiatrists are fully qualified physicians (medical doctors) who specialize in treating people defined as having psychiatric problems. As physicians, psychiatrists have the right to prescribe drugs or electroshock, to hospitalize patients, and to treat people against their will. They are the only mental health professionals who routinely exercise these powers.[*] Psychiatry sets the tone and direction for the field of mental health and has been rapidly pushing it toward a more biological or medical viewpoint.

Psychotherapists are a very broad group which includes anyone helping people with problems by talking with them. Not all psychiatrists are psychotherapists or “talking doctors.” As this book will discuss, many psychiatrists have little or no training in how to communicate with people about their problems. Instead they are trained in making “medical” diagnoses and giving drugs and electroshock.

Psychologists are educated in graduate schools of psychology rather than in medical schools, and they receive a Ph.D. rather than an M.D. Clinical psychologists are given training that overlaps with psychiatrists, and they often receive much more intensive training in psychotherapy than do psychiatrists. Sometimes they work side-by-side with psychiatrists in mental health facilities, but they usually exercise much less authority.

In addition to psychiatrists and psychologists, many other professionals also offer psychotherapy, including clinical social workers, counselors, family therapists, some nurses, some ministers, and a variety of lay people.

Psychoanalysis is the form of psychotherapy founded and developed by Sigmund Freud and taught in his independently franchised psychoanalytic institutes. In the public’s mind, psychoanalysis is correctly associated with the couch, the note pad, and the silent listener. But psychoanalysis is often incorrectly equated with psychiatry. Contrary to popular belief, Freud was not the father of psychiatry. Psychiatry existed long before Freud, and has been largely hostile to his teachings. Freud did not become a psychiatrist, and he warned his colleagues to beware of the medical profession.[*] Nonetheless, psychiatry took over and overwhelmed psychoanalysis in the United States. Very few psychiatrists have become psychoanalysts, and psychoanalysis has very little influence in modern psychiatry.

The author is a psychiatrist and a psychotherapist. He is not a psychoanalyst.

The main critique in this book is aimed at the medical specialty of psychiatry. Unfortunately, since psychiatry dominates the mental health profession, much of what is wrong with psychiatry is also wrong with the whole field.

____________

*Psychologists sometimes have the right to admit patients to mental hospitals. Some psychologists are also trying to obtain the training and the right to prescribe drugs. In other words, they want to obtain more of the powers traditionally monopolized by psychiatrists as medical doctors. When I give talks and workshops for psychologists, I advise them to remain as separate as possible from psychiatry. I am concerned that the public’s ability to find nonmedical alternatives is becoming increasingly limited.

*See Sigmund Freud, The Question of Lay Analysis (Norton, 1964). For a critique, see Philip Rieff, Freud: The Mind of the Moralist (Doubleday, 1961).

Notes

Acknowledgments

 1.  In 1987 the National Alliance for the Mentally Ill brought a complaint against my medical license in the State of Maryland, because I had criticized psychiatric drugs on Oprah Winfrey’s national TV talk show. Although I was not aware of NAMI at the time, I soon learned that it is a large, powerful organization representing the parents of mentally disturbed or incapacited individuals. NAMI is closely connected to establishment psychiatry, and its leadership supports everything I have been criticizing for years: biological and genetic theories, involuntary treatment, heavy reliance on drugs, electroshock, and even lobotomy. (NAMI’s positions will be elaborated throughout the book.) The NAMI attack became a major confrontation over my reform work.

After a hearing, the Maryland Commission on Medical Discipline completely exonerated me in a letter dated October 1, 1987, declaring that there was “no legal violation or ethical impropriety” on my part. The commission even expunged the record and said, “This entire matter is essentially a free speech issue.” Its letter concluded by informing me, “We wish to thank you for having been concerned with [the] assurance of quality health care services in Maryland.” In “Medical Probe: Penalty Is Ruled Out for Bethesda Psychiatrist,” the October 1, 1987, Baltimore Sun quoted the chair of the Maryland Commission on Medical Discipline: “… we dismissed the whole affair and expunged it from the commission’s records.”

The publicity surrounding the attack proved to be a great boost to my reform efforts. At the time, I had been losing my enthusiasm after two decades or more of reform efforts; but the overwhelmingly positive response from individuals and groups throughout the country revitalized my efforts, made me many new friends and colleagues, and led to the writing of this book.

For further information on the attack, see three articles by Daniel Goleman in the New York Times: “Free Expression or Irresponsibility? Psychiatrist Faces Test Today” (September 22, 1987), “Psychiatrist Says Panel Cleared Him” (September 24, 1987), and “Psychiatrist Is Cleared in Case” (October 13, 1987); and two articles by Susan Schmidt in the Washington Post: “Psychiatrist’s TV Comments Prompt Md. Probe” (September 19, 1987), and “Doctor Says Md. Medical Panel Cleared Him” (September 23, 1990). Also see “Complaint Against Psychiatrist Critic of Biologic Therapy Dismissed,” Clinical Psychiatry News, November 1987.

Chapter 1

 1.  Carter Umbarger, Andrew Morrison, James Dalsimer, and Peter Breggin, College Students in a Mental Hospital: An Account of Organized Social Contacts Between College Volunteers and Mental Patients in a Hospital Community (New York: Grune and Stratton, 1962). Also see P. Breggin, “The College Student and the Mental Patient,” in proceedings of the College Student Companion Conference, November 7–9, 1962 (Connecticut State Department of Mental Health and NIMH).

 2.  Throughout the 1970s I devoted much of my time to creating the campaign to abort the return of lobotomy and newer forms of psychiatric brain surgery, such as cingulotomy and amygdalotomy. My efforts included founding the Center for the Study of Psychiatry; educating the public through the media; writing articles for the profession; publishing independent follow-up studies and holding press conferences about individual patients whom the neurosurgeons and psychiatrists had falsely claimed to cure; testifying in malpractice suits and in the landmark Kaimowitz decision (the suit was brought by attorney Gabe Kaimowitz) that ended psychosurgical experimentation in the state mental hospitals; disclosing the racist motivations behind some of the best-known surgical projects; and writing the legislation that created the federal Psychosurgery Commission, which declared the treatment experimental and unsuitable for routine clinical use. The campaign was largely successful, and probably fewer than two hundred operations a year are done in the United States at present. Descriptions of my efforts can be found in newspaper and magazine reports from that period, such as: B. J. Mason, “New Threat to Blacks: Brain Surgery to Control Behavior,” Ebony, February 1973, pp. 63–72; J. Dietz, “Boston’s Psychosurgery: Success and Controversy,” Boston Sunday Globe, January 21, 1973, p. Al; J. Dietz, “Opponent Sees ‘Grave Danger’ in New Psychosurgery Effort by Hub Team,” Boston Globe, May 24, 1973, p. 43; and R. Trotter, “Peter Breggin’s Private War,” Human Behavior, November 1973, pp. 50–77. A more complete list can be found in P. Breggin, “Brain-Disabling Therapies,” in The Psychosurgery Debate, ed. E. Valenstein (San Francisco: W. H. Freeman, 1980). Also see chapter 3 for further citations on psychosurgery and the antipsychosurgery campaign.

Chapter 2

 1.  See H. Fireside, Soviet Psychoprisons (New York: Norton, 1979); and S. Block and P. Reddaway, Psychiatric Terror (New York: Basic Books, 1977).

 2.  For example, see A. Boisen, “Onset in Acute Schizophrenia,” Psychiatry 10 (1947): 159–206; and A. Boisen, “The Genesis and Significance of Mystical Identification in Cases of Mental Disorder,” Psychiatry 15 (1952): 287–96. For Boisen, not only does mysticism illuminate madness, but the study of madness clarifies the experience of Jesus and other prophets.

 3.  See D. Shutts, Lobotomy: Resort to the Knife (New York: Van Nostrand Reinhold, 1982); and E. Valenstein, Great and Desperate Cures (New York: Basic Books, 1986).

Chapter 3

 1.  An exception is T. van Putten and P. May, “Akinetic Depression in Schizophrenia,” Archives of General Psychiatry 35 (1978): 1101–7. The quotes at the beginning of the chapter are typical of patient responses to the drugs. Additional graphic descriptions can be found in many books by survivors (see appendix B).

 2.  Heidi Hensen et al., Stereotactic Psychosurgery (Munksgaard Copenhagen, 1982), Acta Psychiatrica Scandinavica 66, suppl. 301.

 3.  As summarized in chapter 1, in the text and in an endnote, much of my time in the early 1970s was devoted to stopping the return of lobotomy and psychosurgery. My reviews and analyses, which describe the effects of this brain mutilation, include: “The Return of Lobotomy and Psychosurgery” (1973), reprinted with a new introduction in Psychiatry and Ethics, ed. R. B. Edwards (Buffalo N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1982); “Psychosurgery for Political Purposes,” Duquesne Law Review 13 (1975): 841–62; “Brain-Disabling Therapies,” in The Psychosurgery Debate, ed. E. Valenstein (San Francisco: W. H. Freeman, 1980); and “Psychosurgery as Brain-Disabling Therapy,” in Divergent Views in Psychiatry, ed. M. Dongier and D. Wittkower (Hagerstown, Md.: Harper and Row, 1981).

 4.  Thomas Szasz, “Some Observations on the Use of Tranquilizing Drugs,” Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry 77 (1957): 86–92.

 5.  For further discussion of neuroleptic-caused lobotomy effects, see P. Breggin, Psychiatric Drugs: Hazards to the Brain (New York: Springer, 1983); and P. Breggin, “Brain Damage, Dementia and Persistent Cognitive Dysfunction Associated with Neuroleptic Drugs: Evidence, Etiology, Implications,” Journal of Mind and Behavior 11, nos. 3 and 4 (summer and autumn 1990): 425–64.

 6.  I discuss the brain-disabling hypothesis in Psychiatric Drugs: Hazards to the Brain; and “Iatrogenic Helplessness in Authoritarian Psychiatry,” in The Iatrogenics Handbook, ed. R. Morgan (Toronto: IPI Publishing, 1983).

 7.  For further analysis of deinstitutionalization, see L. Mosher and L. Burti, Community Mental Health (New York: W. W. Norton, 1989); P. Brown, The Transfer of Care (Boston: Routledge and Kegan Paul, 1985); C. Warren, “New Forms of Social Control: The Myth of Deinstitutionalization,” American Behavioral Scientist 24 (1981): 724–40; and Andrew Scull, Decarceration: Community Treatment and the Deviant; A Radical View (Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice Hall, 1977). For the APA’s approach to the homeless, including involuntary drugging, see H. R. Lamb, ed., The Homeless Mentally Ill (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 1984).

Chapter 4

 1.  In addition to my 1983 book, a good source on the frequency and severity of neuroleptic-induced neurological effects are the research papers of Theodore van Putten in the Archives of General Psychiatry, pp. 67–72 and 102–5 (vol. 31, 1974), 1101–7 (vol. 35, 1978), and 187–90 (vol. 38, 1981); in Comprehensive Psychiatry (vol. 16, 1975): 43–47; and in Psychopharmacological Bulletin (vol. 16, 1980): 36–38. For one of the few comparisons between lethargic encephalitis and neuroleptic effects, see Henry Brill in the American Handbook of Psychiatry (vol. 2, 1959): 1163–74.

 2.  F. Ayd, Jr. and B. Blackwell, eds., Discoveries in Biological Psychiatry (Philadelphia: Lippincott, 1970).

 3.  The Mental Commitment of M. P., in the Supreme Court of Indiana, Court of Appeals no. 2–1185 A 355, Supreme Court no. 49S02–8707–CV–704. 1987.

 4.  C. Thomas Gualtieri and Robert Sovner, “Akathisia and Tardive Akathisia,” Psychiatric Aspects of Mental Retardation 8, no. 12 (December 1989). This is a good source on tardive akathisia. My book Psychiatric Drugs: Hazards to the Brain (New York: Springer, 1983) contains a discussion of akathisia in general, with references. Current information also can be obtained from the survivor-founded Tardive Dyskinesia/Tardive Dystonia Foundation, 4244 University Way NE, P.O. Box 45732, Seattle, Wash. 98145.

 5.  The true rates are almost surely higher than those reported in the vast majority of studies. It generally is agreed that tardive dyskinesia rates have been going up since the original APA estimates. The increased rate may be due to the wider use of long-acting injections, which make it impossible for patients to avoid taking the medications, as they can when it is given out as pills. Except for those involving long-acting injections, all studies are likely to underestimate the rates for tardive dyskinesia, because a larger percentage of patients always manage to get away without taking their medications. Therefore, they are not being exposed to the risk of tardive dyskinesia, even though they are in the studies. Dilip Jeste and Richard Jed Wyatt note medication rejection rates of 25 to 50 percent in outpatient clinics. Joseph Comaty and Philip Janicak, in the July 1987 Psychiatric Annals, cite noncompliance rates of 11 to 19 percent in hospitalized patients. The rates are also artificially low, because most patients—up to 90 percent—deny their symptoms. If the patients won’t report their symptoms, and if the researchers typically examine them for only five or ten minutes, many cases are going to be missed. Frequently symptoms will appear or worsen when the patient is tired or stressed. Furthermore, as already noted, the drugs tend to mask the symptoms, and since most studies are conducted on drugged patients, the rates again will be too low. Also, the patients are followed for only a fraction of their lives, and even for only a fraction of the time during which they are exposed to the drugs. Many won’t develop the tardive dyskinesia until after the study is over. Lifetime studies are not yet available.

 6.  Journal of Mind and Behavior 11, nos. 3 and 4 (summer and autumn 1990). See appendix B, section 1, David Cohen, for availability.

 7.  Igor Grant and Kenneth Adams, eds., Neuropsychological Assessment of Neuropsychiatric Disorders (New York: Oxford University Press, 1986).

 8.  Psychiatrist Larry Lehmann, quoted by Ron Winslow, “Sandoz Corp.’s Clozaril Treats Schizophrenia but Can Kill Patients,” Wall Street Journal, May 14, 1990.

 9.  Daniel Goleman, “Schizophrenic Drug Hailed, Except for Cost,” New York Times, May 15, 1990. The article provides further confirmation of psychiatry’s unwillingness to take seriously the dangers of its drugs. According to Sandoz, the special monitoring program was necessary because “During our clinical trials we found that about 80% of psychiatrists, all at very good hospitals, became complacent about the blood tests and failed to keep them up, and the blood disease can occur at any point, even after months or years.”

10 See, for example, “New Approaches to Treatment-Resistant Schizophrenia,” a series of articles in the Journal of Clinical Psychiatry, monograph series, vol. 8, no. 1 (May 1990).

11 See, for example, John Waddington and Timothy Crow, “Abnormal Involuntary Movements and Psychosis in the Preneuroleptic Era and in Unmedicated Patients; implications for the Concept of Tardive Dyskinesia,” in Tardive Dyskinesia: Biological Mechanisms and Clinical Aspects, ed. Marion Wolf and Aron Mosnaim (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Press, 1988). While not denying the reality of tardive dyskinesia, the authors try to suggest that the picture is complicated by spontaneous dyskinesias in psychotic patients. The remainder of the volume contains studies demonstrating that tardive dyskinesia exists, that the rates are high, and that spontaneous dyskinesias are rare indeed, even among the elderly, where the highest frequency is to be expected.

12 See, for example, P. M. Schyve et al., “Neuroleptic-Induced Prolactin Level Elevation and Breast Cancer: An Emerging Issue,” Archives of General Psychiatry 35 (1978): 1291–1301; and J. E. Overall, “Prior Psychiatric Treatment and the Development of Breast Cancer,” Archives of General Psychiatry 35 (1978): 898–99. The 1990 PDR (see Thorazine, p. 2109) gives a surprisingly long discussion of the danger and mentions that chronic neuroleptic exposure increases mammary cancer in rodents. It also notes a menacing relationship between prolactin output, which is increased by the neuroleptics, and breast cancer. However, it finds that “the available evidence is considered too limited to be conclusive at this time.” Similar data in regard to a drug given to any group other than “female mental patients” surely would raise grave concern at the FDA and among physicians. Instead the danger goes largely unnoticed in psychiatry and is not mentioned in major textbooks.

13 David Hill, “Opinion: The Problem with Major Tranquillisers,” Openmind, no. 13 (February/March 1985).

Chapter 5

 1.  Benno Muller-Hill, Murderous Science: Elimination by Scientific Selection of Jews, Gypsies, and Others. Germany 1933–1945 (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1988), 88. See appendix B, section 6, for other books and articles describing the role of psychiatry in the mass murder of mental patients and then in helping to bring about the wider holocaust.

 2.  I am grateful to Jeffrey Masson for pointing out the importance of this book to me.

 3.  J. H. Powell, Bring Out Your Dead: The Great Plague of Yellow Fever in Philadelphia in 1793 (New York: Time Reading Program, Special Edition, 1965). I am grateful to Ginger Ross-Breggin for bringing this important book to my attention.

 4.  For a discussion of Heath, see Peter Breggin, “The Return of Lobotomy and Psychosurgery,” in Psychiatry and Ethics, ed. Rem B. Edwards (Buffalo, N.Y.: Prometheus, 1982).

 5.  For a review of tardive dyskinesia and brain damage, see Peter Breggin, “Brain Damage, Dementia and Persistent Cognitive Dysfunction Associated with Neuroleptic Drugs: Evidence, Etiology, Implications,” Journal of Mind and Behavior 11, nos. 3 and 4 (summer and autumn 1990): 425–64.

Chapter 6

 1.  In Heinz and Rowena Ansbacher, eds., The Individual Psychology of Alfred Adler (New York: Basic Books, 1956), 322–23. For a variety of contemporary views of elation and mania, see E. Mark Stern, ed., Psychotherapy of the Grandiose Patient (New York: Haworth Press, 1989).

Chapter 7

 1.  The interested reader may want to refer to any current textbook; S. Ankier and B. Leonard, “Biological Aspects of Depression,” International Review of Neurobiology 28 (1986): 183–239; or L. Siever and K. Davis, “Overview: Toward a Dysregulation Hypothesis of Depression,” American Journal of Psychiatry 142 (1985): 1017–31. As in every other aspect of psychiatry, there are many highly speculative hypotheses, but no firm ones, and no proof that mood disorders have a biological basis.

Chapter 8

 1.  Most textbooks do not give withdrawal problems as much attention as this book does. In addition to those already mentioned in the text, two sources of information on withdrawal are Barbara Geller et al., “Prospective Study of Scheduled Withdrawal from Nortriptyline in Children and Adolescents,” Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology 7 (1987): 252–54; and Steven Dilsaver, “Managing Withdrawal from Antidepressants Requires Keen Eye,” Psychiatric Times, March 1989.

 2.  For example, see Steven Dilsaver et al., “Antidepressant Withdrawal Syndromes: Phenomenology and Pathophysiology,” International Clinical Psychopharmacology 2 (1987): 1–19; and Steven Dilsaver et al., “Amitriptyline Supersensitizes a Central Cholinergic Mechanism,” Biological Psychiatry 22 (1987): 495–507.

 3.  Ramzy Yassa et al., “Tardive Dyskinesia in the Course of Antidepressant Therapy: A Prevalence Study and Review of the Literature,” Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology 7 (1987): 243–46.

 4.  For a brief listing of studies of brain atrophy in affective disorders, see George Jaskiw, Nancy Andreasen, and Daniel Weinberger, “X-Ray Computed Tomography and Magnetic Resonance Imaging in Psychiatry,” American Psychiatric Association Annual Review 6 (1987): 260–99. This team of investigators is radically biological, and their entire thrust is to blame the patient’s supposed mental illness rather than the obviously damaging treatments. As if by fiat, individual studies sometimes declare, without further explanation, that electroshock and drugs are not the cause of the brain shrinkage. See Ronald Rieder et al., “Computed Tomography Scans in Patients with Schizophrenic, Schizoaffective, and Bipolar Affective Disorder,” Archives of General Psychiatry 40 (1983): 735–39.

 5.  For further information on depression and suicide, see I. Oswald et al., “On the Slowness of Action of Tricyclic Antidepressant Drugs,” British Journal of Psychiatry 120 (1972): 673–77.

 6.  The June 1990 Health Letter, published by the Public Citizen Health Research Group, lists many categories of drugs that can cause depression, including barbiturates, minor tranquilizers, numerous heart and blood pressure medications, ulcer drugs, corticosteroids, some antibiotics, anticonvulsants, antiparkinsonian drugs, diet pills, painkillers, and Antabuse. The Public Citizen Health Research Group tends to favor the more potent psychiatric medications and does not list three of the worst offenders: neuroleptics, antidepressants, and lithium.

 7.  See J. M. Strayhorn, Jr., Foundations of Clinical Psychiatry (Chicago: Yearbook Medical Publishers, 1982), 306; and Armand Nicholi, Jr., The New Harvard Guide to Psychiatry (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1988), 509–10.

 8.  Seymour Fisher and Roger Greenberg, in their 1989 book The Limits of Biological Treatments for Psychological Distress, appendix B, section 3, underscore the necessity of control groups using active placebos that cause side effects. Their in-depth review suggests that antidepressants may have no greater impact than an active placebo. They conclude that despite decades of clinical use, the therapeutic effect of the antidepressants remains unconfirmed and a matter of grave concern. In the July 1979 Annals of Internal Medicine (pp. 106–10), J. S. Goodwin and his associates write about the “Knowledge and Use of Placebos by House Officers and Nurses.” They confirm that “the Placebo Effect has been responsible for the efficacy of the great majority of therapies throughout the history of medicine.” But the power of placebo is even more evident in psychiatry than it is in medicine in general.

 9.  Also see, for example, Jerrold Rosenbaum, “The Media and the ‘Miracle Drug’: Risks, Benefits of Treating Depression,” Psychiatric Times, October 1990; Anastasia Toufexis, “Warnings About a Miracle Drug,” Time, July 30, 1990; John Kifner, “Police Say Kahane [Murder] Suspect Took Anti-Depressant Drugs,” New York Times, November 9, 1990; and “More Cases Have Been Filed Against Manufacturer of Antidepressant,” Psychiatric Times, October 1990.

10. In the February 1990 American Journal of Psychiatry (147:207–10), Martin Teicher, Carol Glod, and Jonathan O. Cole report on six depressed patients, previously free of recent suicidal ideation, who developed “intense, violent suicidal preoccupations after 2–7 weeks of fluoxetine treatment.” The suicidal preoccupations lasted from three days to three months after termination of the treatment. The report estimates that 3.5 percent of Prozac users were at risk. While denying the validity of the study, Dista Products, a division of Eli Lilly, put out a brochure for doctors dated August 31, 1990, stating that it was adding “suicidal ideation” to the adverse events section of its Prozac product information.

11. See chapter 7 and studies and commentaries in the vol. 51, April 1990 issue of the Journal of Clinical Psychiatry entitled “Serotonin and Its Effects on Human Behavior” and in S. Brown and J. M. van Praag, eds., The Role of Serotonin in Psychiatric Disorders (New York: Brunner/Mazel, 1991).

12. See S. A. Welner et al., “Autographic Quantification of Serotonin1A Receptors in Rat Brain Following Antidepressant Drug Treatment,” Synapse 4 (1989): 347–52; F. Sulser, “Serotonin-Norepinephrine Receptor Interactions in the Brain: Implications for the Pharmacology and Pathophysiology of Affective Disorders,” Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 48 (1987): 12–18; and J. Wamsley et al., “Receptor Alterations Associated with Serotonergic Agents: An Autoradiographic Analysis,” Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 48 (1987): 19–25.

13. Alfred Goodman et al., eds., Goodman and Gilman’s The Pharmacological Basis of Therapeutics, 7th ed. (New York: Macmillan, 1985), 550.

14. Many people do not develop a “high” from Prozac, but their feeling of increased well-being may be a subtle high. Relatively small doses of any stimulant, including amphetamine or cocaine, may increase the sense of well-being without producing a gross high or euphoria.

15. Many sources report frequent signs of an organic brain syndrome in routine antidepressant treatment—for example, A. B. Wells and M. Mendelson, “Antidepressants,” in Mind-Influencing Drugs, ed. M. Goldberg and G. Egelston (Littleton, Mass.: PSG, 1978). They write, “Patients say that they forget what they are saying in mid-sentence, or forget where they placed things. Reassurance is necessary, especially for older patients, who may fear they are becoming senile.” We shall find that ECT also causes memory dysfunction, but that shock doctors almost uniformly tell patients that it is due to their “mental illness” rather than to the shock.

16. M. Schou, A. Amidsen, and K. Thomsen, “The Effect of Lithium on the Normal Mind,” in De Psychiatria Progrendiente, vol. 2, ed. P. Baudiš, E. Peterová, and V. Sedivec (Plzen, 1968), 712–21.

17. For pediatric references, see Lawrence Kerns, “Treatment of Mental Disorders in Pregnancy,” Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease 174 (1986): 652–59; Gordon Johnson, “Lithium,” Medical Journal of Australia, October 27, 1984, pp. 595–601; and Peter Breggin, Psychiatric Drugs: Hazards to the Brain (New York: Springer, 1983), 194.

18. See Rose Salata and Irwin Klein, “Effects of Lithium on the Endocrine System: A Review,” Journal of Laboratory and Clinical Medicine 110 (1987): 130–36.

19. An exception is Rudra Prakash, “A Review of Hematologic Side Effects of Lithium,” Hospital and Community Psychiatry 36 (1985): 127–28.

Chapter 9

 1.  See C. Miller Fisher, “Neurologic Fragments. II. Remarks on Anosognosia, Confabulation, Memory, and Other Topics; and an Appendix on Self-Observation,” Neurology 39 (1989): 127–32. Fisher describes how brain-injured patients tend to deny their mental losses and to “confabulate” or make up stories to cover their deficits. The general tendency, called anosognosia or unawareness of neurologic deficit, is so common that Fisher declares, “Indeed, it may qualify as one of the general rules of cerebral dysfunction.” Yet shock advocates persistently claim that ECT-damaged patients exaggerate their memory loss.

 2.  APA task force report: The Practice of Electroconvulsive Therapy: Recommendations for Treatment, Training, and Privileging (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 1990). The task force, chaired by Richard Weiner and including Max Fink and Harold Sacheim, two other defenders of shock treatment, set out to exonerate the “treatment.”

 3.  See James L. Bernat and Frederick Vincent, eds., Neurology: Problems in Primary Care (Oradell, N.J.: Medical Economics, 1987). In discussing “Minor Closed Head Injury” they state, “The patient who is not fully oriented at the time of evaluation and who demonstrates defective immediate recall and recent memory should be hospitalized for 24 to 48 hours.” Shock patients are typically much more impaired and are suffering from what would be called severe head injury by neurological standards.

 4.  Edward Babayan, The Structure of Psychiatry in the Soviet Union (New York: International Press, 1985). For criticism of shock, see pages 36–37, 53, 134–35, and 294.

 5.  In the June 1960 American Journal of Psychiatry psychiatrist and shock advocate David Impastato describes the drama surrounding the first shock treatment in Italy. An involuntary patient had been subjected to one shock, which failed to make him convulse. “The Professor [Ugo Cerletti] suggested that another treatment with a higher voltage be given. The staff objected. They stated that if another treatment were given the patient would probably die and wanted further treatment postponed until the morrow. The Professor knew what that meant. [Presumably, that they would refuse to participate again.] He decided to go ahead right then and there, but before he could say so the patient suddenly sat up and pontifically proclaimed no longer in jargon, but in clear Italian, “Non una seconda! Mortifere!” (Not again, it will kill me.) This made the Professor think and swallow, but his courage was not lost. He gave the order to proceed at a higher voltage and a longer time; and the first electroconvulsion in man ensued. Thus was born EST out of one man and over the objection of his assistants.”

 6.  Gary Aden, “The International Psychiatric Association for the Advancement of Electrotherapy: A Brief History,” American Journal of Social Psychiatry 4, no. 4 (1984): 9–10.

 7.  Alison Bass, “McLean Hires Back Doctor Ordered to Quit,” Boston Globe, February 10, 1989.

 8.  The $200 to $300 figure was given by psychiatrists at the Alioto hearings.

 9.  The availability of dangerous but remunerative technology encourages exploitation in other fields of medicine as well. See the Associated Press, “Doctors Owning Machines X-Ray Patients More Often: Study Shows Some Evidence of Exploitation,” Washington Post, December 6, 1990, p. A7.

10. Deposition of Glen N. Peterson in John Doe vs. D. Michael O’Connor et al., Defendants, vol. 2, in the Superior Court of the State of California in and for the County of Los Angeles, no. C 646 194, CSR no. 3081, March 18, 1988.

11. Peterson said in his deposition that the woman had received four series of shock treatments prior to his administering 130–140 more. A series usually consists of at least six or eight treatments, and sometimes more. He also said that he was using the “upper end of the scale” of electrical energy, 150–170 volts. Depending on other electrical parameters, this could be in excess of household current.

12. Numerous studies of the brain-damaging effects of such large doses are cited in my book Electroshock: Its Brain-Disabling Effects (New York: Springer, 1979). See, for example, A. I. Rabin, “Persons Who Received More than 100 Electric Shock Treatments,” Journal of Personality 17 (1948): 42–47; D. I. Templer et al., “Cognitive Functioning and Degree of Psychosis in Schizophrenics Given Many Electroconvulsive Treatments,” British Journal of Psychiatry 123 (1973): 441–43; and A. Ferraro and L. Roizen, “Cerebral Morphologic Changes in Monkeys Subjected to a Large Number of Electrically Induced Convulsions,” American Journal of Psychiatry 106 (1949): 278–84.

13. See the advertisement “Informed ECT, at Last,” in Psychiatric News, September 7, 1990, p. 3.

14. Figures through 1983 are available in Carol Warren, “Electroconvulsive Therapy: ‘New’ Treatment of the 1980s,” Research in Law, Deviance and Social Control 8 (1986): 41–55. More recent figures are from the State of California, Department of Mental Health, Statistics and Data Analysis Section, July 20, 1989.

15. See, for example, E. N. Zamora and R. Kaebling, “Memory and Electroconvulsive Therapy,” American Journal of Psychiatry 122 (1965): 546–54. For a complete review, see Peter Breggin, Electroshock: Its Brain-Disabling Effects, 63–70.

16. Also see Lewis Rowland, ed., Merritt’s Textbook of Neurology, 8th ed. (Philadelphia: Lea and Fibiger, 1989). As with many other observations in this book, the comparison between ECT and closed-head injury did not fully dawn on me until emphasized by a survivor of the treatment.

17. I have reviewed the animal studies in detail in Electroshock: Its Brain-Disabling Effects. For short summaries, see Peter Breggin, “Neuropathology and Cognitive Dysfunction from ECT,” Psychopharmacology Bulletin 22, no. 2 (1986): 476–79; Peter Breggin, “Disabling the Brain with Electroshock,” in Divergent Views in Psychiatry, ed. M. Dongier and E. Wittkower (Hagerstown, Md.: Harper and Row, 1981); and John Friedberg, “Shock Treatment, Brain Damage, and Memory Loss: A Neurological Perspective,” American Journal of Psychiatry 134 (1977): 1010–14.

While psychiatrists tend to deny what shock is doing to their patients, psychologists have sometimes been more open about it. James McConnel, in Understanding Human Behavior, 4th ed. (New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1983), reviews my conclusions that ECT effects are “severe,” “catastrophic,” and “devastating” and concludes, “Most of the literature on ECT tends to support Breggin’s view” (p. 565).

18. See note 13, this chapter.

19. See Peter Breggin, Electroshock: Its Brain-Disabling Effects.

20. In Max Rinkel and Harold Himwich, eds., Insulin Treatment in Psychiatry (New York: Philosophical Library, 1959), shock advocate Hans Hoff states that the object of ECT is to kill brain cells: “cells that are sick, and new brain cells which are potentially sick have to be destroyed. Otherwise relapses will come. This means that one of the most important things is to see that really every cell which is affected is really destroyed” (p. 222). In 1941 Walter Freeman was given space in the prestigious journal Diseases of the Nervous System (vol. 2) to publish an editorial entitled “Brain-Damaging Therapeutics.” Freeman postulates, “Among the explanations advanced to account for the success of the various shock methods of therapy in the psychoses, that of actual damage to the brain has not received adequate attention.” He declares, “Maybe it will be shown that a mentally ill patient can think more clearly and more constructively with less brain in actual operation.” Similarly, in a commentary at the end of an article by F. Ebaugh and others in the 1942 Transactions of the American Neurological Association (pp. 35–41), one of America’s most influential psychiatrists, Abraham Myerson, speaks of how mental patients have “more intelligence than they can handle and that the reduction of intelligence is an important factor in the curative process.” His remarks are made in a discussion of autopsy material gained from patients who died from electroshock treatment.

21. R. L. Kahn, M. Fink, and E. A. Weinstein, “Relation of Amobarbital to Clinical Improvement in Electroshock,” Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry 76 (1956): 23–29. In a study of the amobarbital interview method, the authors again make clear that the test is useful as a “diagnostic test for the existence of structural brain disease.” This is the test that is correlated with a positive clinical outcome following ECT. The meaning is clear: brain damage is considered an improvement. See R. L. Kahn, M. Fink, and E. Weinstein: “The ‘Amytal Test’ in Patients with Mental Illness,” Journal of the Hillside Hospital 4 (1955): 3–13.

22. Fink’s articles, which are cited in my 1979 book on shock, include those in the Journal of the Hillside Hospital 6 (1957): 197–206; Archives of Neurology and Psychiatry 80 (1958): 380–86; and Diseases of the Nervous System 19 (1958): 113–18. In his book Convulsive Therapy: Theory and Practice (New York: Raven, 1973), Fink again makes clear that the degree of improvement is correlated with brain dysfunction as reflected by psychological tests, brain wave studies, and other criteria (p. 127). He points out that “patients become more compliant and acquiescent with treatment” (p. 139) and also continues to connect improvement with denial, disorientation, brain trauma, cerebral dysfunction, and signs of an organic brain syndrome (p. 165). He also mentions anosognosia, the denial of physical damage after trauma to the brain, as a basis for the improvement. Nonetheless, in public Fink has contested my assertion that shock works by producing damage and dysfunction.

23. Max Fink, “Efficacy and Safety of Induced Seizures (EST) in Man,” Comprehensive Psychiatry 19 (1978). This quote and several others originally were located by shock survivor Marilyn Rice.

24. For a discussion of anosognosia, see note 1 of this chapter.

25. Russ Rymer, “Electroshock,” Hippocrates, March/April 1989.

26. See David Remnick, “25 Years of Nightmares: Victims of CIA-Funded Mind Experiments Seek Damages from the Agency,” Washington Post, July 28, 1985; Lee Hockstander, “Victims of 1950’s Mind-Control Experiments Settle with CIA,” Washington Post, October 5, 1988; Leonard Rubenstein, “The CIA and the Evil Doctor,” New York Times, November 7, 1988; and a letter by Don Weitz, “Psychiatry Bears Guilt in Brainwashing Tests,” New York Times, November 26, 1988.

27. See the classic article by A. V. Delgado-Escueta et al., “Management of Status Epilepticus,” New England Journal of Medicine 306 (1982): 1337–40; or James Bernat and Frederick Vincent, eds., Neurology: Problems in Primary Care (Oradell, N.J.: Medical Economics, 1987), which states that status epilepticus is “a true medical emergency.”

28. In the British Journal of Psychiatry (142 [1983]: 1–8), Larry Squire and Pamela Slater surveyed more than sixty patients long after they had received routine shock treatment. Seven months after ECT, patients reported a median memory loss spanning a period of two years prior to and three months after the shock—a total block of twenty-seven months. Three years after shock, they reported a smaller gross loss, from six months prior to two months after the ECT. The estimate at seven months is surely more accurate. Brain-injured patients, as described, tend to deny their losses (see note 1 of this chapter). While it’s very unlikely that the brain would heal any further after seven months, over the years it would become easier for patients to deny the degree of their memory loss. Despite the tendency toward denial, more than half of the patients (55 percent) surveyed by Squire and Slater felt that they had not regained normal memory function over the years. In a personal discussion with me at the 1985 Consensus Conference on ECT, sponsored by NIMH in Bethesda, Maryland, Squire told me that one patient suffered significant memory losses over a span of ten years; but he said he did not consider it important to mention it in his report.

In Multiple-Monitored Electroconvulsive Therapy (Boca Raton, Fla.: CRC Press, 1981), Barry Maletzky reports on a survey of forty-seven patients thirty-six months after his shock program. Thirty-six percent had ongoing or continuing cognitive problems, such as keeping sequences straight and remembering new things: “I have been following this soap opera for five years on TV but now I get confused about who is doing what to whom”; “I couldn’t tell my neighbor how to get over to my uncle’s house when she was driving me there the other day, but I have been going over there for years” (p. 180).

29. Two groups were studied, one with a mean age of 69.7 years and the other 41.7 years. There were control patients as well. None of them had had ECT for at least three months.

30. Nonetheless, the authors remain strong advocates of ECT.

31. Max Fink, Convulsive Therapy: Theory and Practice (New York: Raven, 1973); and Richard Abrams, Electroconvulsive Therapy (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988).

32. One controlled study using simulated ECT, by J. Lambourn and D. Gill, “A Controlled Comparison of Simulated and Real ECT” (British Journal of Psychiatry 133 [1978]: 514–19), found no difference and concludes, “This cast some doubt on current view of the effectiveness of electro-convulsive therapy in general.” Even the often cited shock study, S. Brandon et al., “Electroconvulsive Therapy: Results in Depressive Illness from the Leicestershire Trial” (British Medical Journal 288 [1984]: 22–25), presents a bleak picture of ECT efficacy. While the authors emphasize an improvement on the Hamilton depression rating scale at four weeks, their data show absolutely no difference between shocked patients and sham patients at twelve or twenty-eight weeks. Their whole argument rests on the hope of a mere four weeks’ relief from depression—the period of maximum brain dysfunction. But even in regard to the alleged improvement during the one-month period, the evidence is flimsy at best, relying on a few borderline test results. Wade Hudson summarizes:

Whether due to the power of suggestion, the benefit of routine support from nursing staff, spontaneous healing, or a combination of the three, those who received simulated shock treatment improved dramatically, and on most measures, even 1–3 days right after treatment; [and] they improved as much as did those who had electricity passed through their brains.

33. It’s unclear why shock advocates frequently misrepresent the Avery and Winokur paper, but as I discuss in my 1979 book on shock (pp. 130–31), they may have gotten the wrong impression from Fink’s citation of the paper in a paragraph misleadingly entitled “ECT and Suicide.” On one occasion, a shock doctor tried to use the paper in a radio debate with me to prove the efficacy of shock in preventing suicide, but fortunately I was on the phone from my office and was able to locate the paper to quote it on the air. The Avery and Winokur paper is also misused in the APA task force report, The Practice of Electroconvulsive Therapy (1990), p. 53.

34. On many occasions I have referred to this as the shame of my life.

35. One-sided or unilateral shock can be more damaging than the usual bilateral shock, because the electrodes are placed closer together. The electrical current strikes the brain with more concentrated force, doing more intense focal damage. This is demonstrable in brain wave studies. It also is demonstrable in studies that show increased damage to the verbal centers when the electrodes are placed on the dominant side. Furthermore, attempts to shock the nondominant side will at times end up directing the full force of the shock inadvertently at the verbal centers. Many left-handers and some right-handers are dominant on the same, rather than the opposite, side of the brain.

The dangerousness of unilateral shock is increased by the fact that it is harder to produce a convulsion with it. So sometimes the current controls on the shock machine are turned up higher to deliver a greater shock, or else more than one shock may be needed to produce a seizure. Often additional ECT treatments are given to achieve the desired level of post-ECT brain dysfunction.

Denial and anosognosia are even more pronounced after damage to the nonverbal, or nondominant, side of the brain. Patients with strokes on that side of the brain will not recognize that they have very obvious ill effects, such as paralyzed limbs. Blakeslee remarks that the rest of the brain has trouble recognizing or communicating about any damage to the nonverbal side. Shock advocates are also well aware that nondominant shock makes their patients less aware of the damage done to them. In his 1988 book Electroconvulsive Therapy, Richard Abrams observes that anosognosia is especially “profound and striking” after nondominant shock. Yet shock doctors never admit that this causes patients to report falsely that they have less memory loss or mental dysfunction after nondominant ECT.

36. The relative impact of nondominant shock on nonverbal functions is reviewed in D. Fromm-Auch, “Comparison of Unilateral and Bilateral ECT: Evidence of Selective Memory Impairment,” British Journal of Psychiatry 141 (1982): 608–13.

37. Margaret McDonald, “FDA Orders Tougher ECT Device Standards,” Psychiatric News, December 7, 1979.

38. “Reclassification of ECT Devices Delayed,” Psychiatric News, April 6, 1984.

39. See Rael Jean Isaac, “FDA’s Shocking Treatment of a Valuable Device,” Wall Street Journal, December 5, 1990; and Seth Farber, “US Food & Drug Administration Proposes Giving Electroshock the Rubber Stamp,” Dendron, October 24, 1990. (See appendix A for the availability of Dendron.)

40. M. Boss, “Alte und neue Shocktherapien und Shocktherapeuten,” Zeitschrift fur Neurologie 173 (1941): 776–82.

41. Rex Dalton, “Psychotherapists Having Sex with Patients May Be Jailed,” San Diego Union, September 27, 1989.

42. Rex Dalton, “Psychiatrist’s Former Patient Tells Story of Abuse,” San Diego Union, January 1, 1989.

43. Leonard Frank, “Electroshock: Death, Brain Damage, Memory Loss, and Brainwashing,” Journal of Mind and Behavior 11, nos. 3 and 4 (summer and autumn 1990).

Chapter 10

 1.  For the “party line” on anxiety, see Sandy Rovner, “High Anxiety: Probing the Most Common Mental Disorder,” Washington Post Health, May 22, 1990.

 2.  Peter Breggin, The Psychology of Freedom: Liberty and Love as a Way of Life (Buffalo, N.Y.: Prometheus, 1980).

 3.  For a detailed discussion, see Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders (Revised) (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 1987). The description is excellent but somewhat too rigid in its requirements. It also includes a phenomenon, “numbing of general responsiveness,” that frequently is absent. More often people become oversensitive and hyperreactive.

 4.  See Frank Ochberg, ed., Post-Traumatic Therapy and Victims of Violence (New York: Brunner/Mazel, 1988); and Spencer Eth and Robert Pynoos, eds., Post-Traumatic Stress Disorder in Children (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Press, 1985).

 5.  The American Psychiatric Press’s Textbook of Psychiatry (1988), for example, mentions “growing attention” to the subject and reports that “a number of hypotheses have been put forward that are currently being studied,” but none of them are given primacy or any detailed analysis. George Vaillant’s review of the causes of alcoholism in the New Harvard Guide to Psychiatry (1988) does not even discuss a biological cause for alcoholism. The many findings of biological abnormalities in alcoholics are attributable to toxic effects on the brain, liver, and other organs. When the Supreme Court refused to grant alcoholism the status of disease in Traynor v. Turnage and McKelvey v. Turnage in 1988, a spate of articles pro and con appeared in the press. See Al Kamen, “VA Can Define Alcoholism as Willful Misconduct,’” New York Times, April 21, 1988; Richard Vatz and Lee Weinberg, “There’s a New Skepticism Toward Alcoholism as a Disease,” Washington Post Health, March 7, 1989; and a letter by Jeffrey Schaler, “Alcoholism Is Not a Disease,” Washington Post, October 25, 1988. Also see Herbert Fingarette, Heavy Drinking: The Myth of Alcoholism as a Disease (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1988).

 6.  For a thorough evaluation of genetic studies of alcoholism, see John Searles, “The Role of Genetics in the Pathogenesis of Alcoholism,” Journal of Abnormal Behavior 97 (1988): 153–67. Even genetic researchers in the field who enter with a strong bias toward positive results are forced to limit their claims to evidence for a “gene effect” in “for the less frequent subtype of alcoholism that is marked by early onset, severe alcohol abuse, and sociopathy.” Annabel Bolos et al., “Population and Pedigree Studies Reveal a Lack of Association Between Dopamine D2 Receptor and Gene in Alcoholism,” Journal of the American Medical Association 264 (1990): 3156–60. However, even that meager assertion is unproven. Bolos et al. further admit: “On the other hand, familial transmission studies do not support the existence of a single gene in the majority of alcoholics.” The phrase “single gene” is something of a euphemism, as the authors cite no evidence for multiple gene influences either.

 7.  K. Blum et al., “Allelic Association of Human Dopamine D2 Receptor Gene in Alcoholism,” Journal of the American Medical Association 263 (1990): 2055–60.

 8.  Annabel Bolos et al., “Population and Pedigree Studies Reveal a Lack of Association Between the Dopamine D2 Receptor Gene and Alcoholism,” Journal of the American Medical Association 264 (1990): 3156–60.

 9.  “Alcoholism Gene Report Undercut,” Washington Post, December 26, 1990. The concluding sentence of the study itself is very similar: that their findings are “inconsistent” with a “widespread association” between the receptor gene and alcoholism.

10. Susan Squire, The Slender Balance (New York: G. P. Putnam, 1983).

11. J. Polivy and C. P. Herman, “Dieting and Bingeing: A Causal Analysis,” American Psychologist 40 (1985): 193–201.

12. Hilde Bruch, Eating Disorders: Obesity, Anorexia Nervosa, and the Person Within (New York: Basic Books, 1973).

Chapter 11

 1.  Armand Nicholi, Jr., ed., The New Harvard Guide to Psychiatry (Cambridge, Mass.: Harvard University Press, 1988), 523.

 2.  See any psychiatric textbook or the American Psychiatric Association’s task force report: Benzodiazepine Dependence, Toxicity, and Abuse (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 1990). These drugs are always discussed as a group, with comparisons mostly focused on the duration of action rather than on the actual effect.

 3.  Ibid.

 4.  When it was discovered that benzodiazepines attach to a specific type of receptor in the brain, this was treated as evidence that the drugs have a specifically inhibitory effect on anxiety. In reality the receptors are spread throughout the gray matter of the human brain. See John Talbott et al., Textbook of Psychiatry (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Press, 1988).

 5.  APA task force report, Benzodiazepine Dependence, Toxicity, and Abuse (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 1990), 33.

 6.  See Russell Noyes, Jr., et al., “Benzodiazepine Withdrawal: A Review of the Evidence,” Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 49 (1988): 382–89.

 7.  Since doctors frequently do not pay enough attention to the problem, it is worth pointing to two relevant studies of memory dysfunction. In “The Effect of Diazepam on Patients’ Memory” in the Journal of Clinical Psychopharmacology 4 (1984): 203–6, William Angus and David Romney find that patients taking routine doses of Valium for a minimum of five days did more poorly on both short-term and long-term memory tests than they had done prior to using the medication. Short-term memory was most severely affected. They warn against combining psychotherapy and minor tranquilizers: “Because of the growing body of evidence that diazepam does impair memory, its use as an adjunct to therapies emphasizing learning should be reconsidered. It is possible that diazepam slows down the very learning that is supposed to take place.”

Daljit Mac, Rajiv Kumar, and Donald Goodwin of the University of Kansas Medical Center tested the effect of Ativan on memory in a double-blind study reported in the Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 46 (1985): 137–38. They gave one drug dose or placebo in the morning and then tested the volunteers throughout the day. Recall was reduced two hours after drug ingestion. The authors conclude, “These results support findings by other investigators that lorazepam has a deleterious effect on short-term recall of verbal content. This has implications for students and others preparing for tests or doing mental work while taking therapeutic doses of lorazepam.”

 8.  An exception is Jack M. Gorman, The Essential Guide to Psychiatric Drugs (New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1990). Gorman states: “BuSpar might cause neurological problems (tardive dyskinesia) if taken for many years. In fact, this has not occurred in patients who have taken it, although the drug has been on the market only about three years” (p. 145).

 9.  See, for example, the December 1990 Psychiatric Annals.

10. Indeed, studies have shown no difference between Xanax and Valium in panic disorder. See David Dunner et al., “Effect of Alprazolam and Diazepam on Anxiety and Panic Disorder: A Controlled Study,” Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 47 (1986): 458–60. Drug “efficacy” compared to placebo was not very impressive.

11. Joe Graedon and Dr. Teresa Graedon, “Nervous Breakdown Can Be Drug Induced,” press release for the week of October 30, 1989, from King Features Syndicate (235 East Forty-fifth Street, New York, N.Y. 10017).

12. Chad Carlton, “Xanax: Popular Tranquilizer Creates Anxiety About Abuse, Danger with Alcohol,” Lexington Herald-Leader, August 26, 1990.

13. Reported in identical eight-page advertisements for Xanax in various psychiatric journals, including the December 1990 issues of Psychiatric Annals and the American Journal of Psychiatry. The advertising material is dated October 1990.

14. James C. Ballenger et al., “Alprazolam in Panic Disorder and Agoraphobia: Results from a Multicenter Trial—I: Efficacy in Short-Term Treatment,” Archives of General Psychiatry 45 (1988): 413–22.

15. The figure of “more than 500” is reported in an advertisement for Xanax in Psychiatric Annals (December 1990). For a more complete analysis of the sample size, see Gerald Klerman, “Overview of the Cross-National Collaborative Panic Study,” Archives of General Psychiatry 45 (1988): 407–12; and James Ballenger et al., “Alprazolam in Panic Disorder and Agoraphobia: Results from a Multicenter Trial,” Archives of General Psychiatry 45 (1988): 413–22. Klerman reports that the basic study involved 600 patients, only one-half of whom were taking Xanax, and that another study involved 1,100, only one-third of whom were on Xanax. Ballenger et al. more accurately explain that in the basic study, only 481 of the 526 patients in the placebo and drug groups completed three weeks. By the end of the study there were only 226 Xanax patients remaining.

16. J. C. Pecknold et al., “Alprazolam in Panic Disorder and Agoraphobia: Results from a Multicenter Trial—III: Discontinuation Effects,” Archives of General Psychiatry 45 (1988): 429–37.

17. Russell Noyes, Jr., et al., “Alprazolam in Panic Disorder and Agoraphobia: Results from a Multicenter Trial—II: Patient Acceptance, Side Effects, and Safety,” Archives of General Psychiatry 45 (1988): 423–28.

18. Reported in an advertisement for Xanax in the December 1990 issue of Psychiatric Annals.

19. Rajiv Kumar et al., “Anxiolytics and Memory: A Comparison of Lorazepam and Alprazolam,” Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 48 (1987): 158–60.

20. See, for example, Lewis Baxter et al., “PET Imaging in Obsessive Compulsive Disorder With and Without Depression,” Journal of Clinical Psychiatry 51 (suppl., 1990): 61–69. The paper reviews several studies, including their own, in which five of nine patients were “on a variety of antidepressants, benzodiazepines, and neuroleptics,” while the remaining were drug-free for only two weeks. The authors speculate that the primary damage is to the striatum. This is the area known to be damaged by the neuroleptics (chapter 4) and possibly by the chemically related tricyclic antidepressants.

21. See chapters 1 and 3 for citations concerning my reform work in preventing the resurgence of psychosurgery in the early 1970s.

Chapter 12

 1.  J. Larry Brown and Stephen R. Bing, “Drugging Children: Child Abuse by Professionals,” in Children’s Rights and the Mental Health Professions, ed. Gerald P. Koocher (New York: John Wiley, 1976).

 2.  Spencer Rich, “Child-Abuse Cases Total 2.4 Million,” Washington Post, June 27, 1990.

 3.  Nicholas Zill and Charlotte Schoenborn, “Developmental, Learning, and Emotional Problems: Health of Our Nation’s Children, United States, 1988,” Advance Data from Vital And Health Statistics, no. 190 (Hyattsville, Md.: National Center for Health Statistics, 1990). Also see the Chicago Tribune report, “Problems Found in 1 of 5 Children,” in the Washington Post, December 9, 1990.

 4.  In addition to the books cited in this section, for a recent bibliography of studies on the effect of child abuse on adults, see Janet Surrey et al., “Reported History of Physical and Sexual Abuse and Severity of Symptomatology in Women Psychiatric Patients,” American Journal of Orthopsychiatry 60 (1990): 412–17. In their own investigation, Surrey et al. found that 64 percent of 140 female psychiatric clinic patients reported a history of physical or sexual abuse and that symptoms were more severe among them than among women who reported no abuse. Also see chapter 14 concerning women and abuse.

 5.  Similar points are made in an earlier book: David Wolfe, Child Abuse: Implications for Child Development and Psychopathology (Newbury Park, Calif.: Sage, 1987).

 6.  For inflated estimates, also see Diane McGuinness, “Attention Deficit Disorder: The Emperor’s New Clothes, Animal ‘Pharm,’ and Other Fiction,” in Seymour Fisher and Roger Greenberg, The Limits of Biological Treatments for Psychological Distress (Hillsdale, N.J.: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, 1989), 161.

 7.  Psychologist Russell Barkley, director of neuropsychology at the Medical College of Wisconsin, is one of the most often quoted experts in the field. More balanced than Wender, he is author of Hyperactive Children: A Handbook for Diagnosis and Treatment (New York: Guilford Press, 1981). Barkley recognizes that “the typical picture of the household in which the hyperactive child resides is one of turmoil” and that the children do better when the parents are helped to improve their skills. But he nonetheless concludes that it is the children, and not the parents, who create these “destructive and aversive family situations.” Again like Wender, he finds the children to be especially “energetic, exuberant, bright, inquisitive.” If the child has a whole bunch of these traits, Barkley suggests, they may add up to an “explosive” combination. And so the best and the most beautiful run afoul of some families and schools and then are polished off by the mental health professionals.

 8.  Some of Victor Sanua’s publications include: “Standing Against an Established Ideology: Infantile Autism, a Case in Point,” Clinical Psychologist 40 (fall 1987): 96–100; “The Organic Etiology of Infantile Autism: A Critical Review of the Literature,” International Journal of Neuroscience 30 (1986): 195–225; “Infantile Autism and Childhood Schizophrenia: Review of the Issues from the Sociocultural Point of View,” Social Science and Medicine 17 (1983): 1633–51; “Cultural Changes and Psychopathology in Children: With Special Reference to Infantile Autism,” Acta Paedopsychiatrica 47 (1981): 133–42; “Infantile Autism and Parental Socioeconomic Status: A Case of Bimodal Distribution,” Child Psychiatry and Human Development 17 (1987): 189–98; and “An International Survey of Mental Health Professionals on the Etiology of Infantile Autism,” in Frontiers of Infant Psychiatry, vol. 2, ed. Justin Call et al. (New York: Basic Books, 1985).

 9.  David Simmonds, “Children’s Rights and Family Dysfunction: ‘Daddy, Why Do I Have To Be the Crazy One?’” in Children’s Rights and the Mental Health Professions, ed. Gerald Koocher (New York: John Wiley, 1976). Koocher’s book contains a number of valuable chapters.

Chapter 13

 1.  “Increase in Doctors’ Use of Ritalin for School Kids,” San Francisco Chronicle, October 21, 1988.

 2.  Carole Wade Offir, “Are We Pushers for Our Own Children?” Psychology Today, December 1974.

 3.  “Physician Warns of Dangers in Drugging Children,” Psychiatric News, May 7, 1975.

 4.  See, for example, Timothy Kuehnel and Katherine Slama, “Guidelines for the Developmentally Disabled,” in The Psychiatric Uses of Seclusion and Restraint, ed. Kenneth Tardiff (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Press, 1984), 93–94; Mina Dulcan, “Treatment of Children and Adolescents,” in Textbook of Psychiatry, ed. John Talbott et al. (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Press, 1988); R. Plotkin and K. Rigling, “Invisible Manacles: Drugging Mentally Retarded People,” Stanford Law Review 31 (1979): 637–78; and Peter Breggin, Psychiatric Drugs: Hazards to the Brain (New York: Springer, 1983), 12–32.

 5.  See C. Keith Conners, “Psychopharmacologic Treatment of Children,” in Albert DiMascio and Richard Shader, eds., Clinical Handbook of Psychopharmacology (New York: Science House, 1970), 285.

 6.  See the APA task force report, Treatments of Psychiatric Disorders (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Association, 1989), 374.

 7.  In addition to the sources listed for side effects, see the DSM-III-R description of psychological and behavioral changes associated with Ritalin dependence, which include “depression,” “social isolation,” “anergia” (loss of energy), and “anhedonia” (loss of pleasure).

 8.  For discussions of Ritalin side effects, see John Talbott et al., Textbook of Psychiatry (Washington, D.C.: American Psychiatric Press, 1988), 990–93; M. K. Dulcan, “Comprehensive Treatment of Children and Adolescents with Attention Deficit Disorders; the State of the Art,” Clinical Psychology Review 6 (1986): 539–70; Carol Whalen and Barbara Henker, “The Social Ecology of Psychostimulant Treatment: A Model for Conceptual and Empirical Analysis,” in Hyperactive Children: The Social Ecology of Identification and Treatment, ed. C. Whalen and B. Henker (New York: Academic Press, 1980); and Richard Scarnati, “An Outline of Hazardous Side Effects of Ritalin (Methylphenidate),” International Journal of Addictions 21 (1986):837–41. (Scarnati cites a number of articles documenting psychotic reactions to Ritalin. Mixing Ritalin with other drugs, including antidepressants, can be especially hazardous.) See also Charles Grob and Joseph Coyle, “Suspected Adverse Methylphenidate-Imipramine Interactions in Children,” Journal of Developmental and Behavioral Pediatrics 7 (1986): 265–67.

 9.  Physician Larry Plumlee drew my attention to an irony in a story by Lynda Richardson, “Fairfax Family Battles Legacy of Addiction,” Washington Post, February 6, 1990, which focuses on a family whose son, Andy, is addicted to a variety of drugs, including cocaine. Larry noticed that Andy had been “prescribed medication for hyperactivity at age 9.” Years later, the article reports, the family was told “that his hyperactivity made him predisposed toward addiction.” More likely, as Plumlee suggests, the medication for hyperactivity predisposed him to seek out similar drugs later in life. Later in the article we find out that the mother “has taken more than a dozen medications for depression since the family’s addiction problems became apparent five years ago.” As long as psychiatric drugs are labeled “treatments” while illicit drugs are called “addictions,” the public will remain confused. Psychoactive drugs in general help people escape from their feelings and their real-life problems, shift the locus of control outside the individual, and make it physiologically and psychologically difficult for people to go on living without a chemical crutch.

10. See the several sources already listed for Ritalin side effects and the DSM-III-R (1987) description of symptoms associated with Ritalin dependency, including “irritability,” “attentional disturbances,” and “memory problems.”

11. James Spotts and Carol Spotts, Use and Abuse of Amphetamine and Its Substitutes (Rockville, Md.: National Institute of Drug Abuse, undated, circa 1978).

Chapter 14

 1.  Quoted in “ ‘America Facing Its Most Tragic Moment’—Dr. Carl Jung,” New York Times, September 29, 1912.

 2.  Sigmund Freud, New Introductory Lectures on Psychoanalysis (1932), 183.

 3.  Kate Millett, in Sexual Politics (New York: Ballantine, 1969), is critiquing Freud’s view that women are inherently masochistic.

 4.  Elaine Showalter, The Female Malady: Women, Madness, and English Culture, 1830–1980 (New York: Pantheon, 1985), 19.

 5.  Virginia Raymond et al., “Mental Health and Violence Against Women: A Feminist Ex-Inmate Analysis,” Phoenix Rising, winter 1983. This was a position paper resulting from a workshop at the Tenth Annual International Conference on Human Rights and Psychiatric Oppression, Toronto, May 1982.

 6.  From an unpublished report presented at the Second International Conference on Psychosurgery, Copenhagen, 1970, by R. F. Hetherington, P. Haden, and W. Craig, of the departments of surgery, psychiatry, and psychology, Kingston Psychiatric Hospital and Queens University, Kingston, Ontario. Cited by Peter Breggin, “The Return of Lobotomy and Psychosurgery,” Congressional Record, February 24, 1972. Reprinted with a new introduction in Rem B. Edwards, Psychiatry and Ethics (Buffalo, N.Y.: Prometheus Books, 1982).

 7.  Most recent data are from California. See chapter 9.

 8.  This is the final report of the American Psychological Association Task Force on Women and Depression, Women and Depression: Risk Factors and Treatment Issues (Washington, D.C.: American Psychological Association, 1990). The editors are Ellen McGrath, Gwendolyn Puryear Keita, Bonnie R. Strickland, and Nancy Felipe Russo. The report was not yet available, so the quotes are from an eight-page promotional flier by the same title.

 9.  Malcolm Gladwell, “Women and Depression: Culture Called a Key Factor,” Washington Post, December 6, 1990.

10. Judy Mann, “Our Culture as a Cause of Depression,” Washington Post, December 7, 1990.

11. Peter Breggin, “Psychiatry and Women,” recorded seminar presented at the annual meeting of the National Association for Rights Protection and Advocacy (NARPA), Miami Lakes, Florida. See appendix B for availability.

12. Jeffrey Masson, Freud: The Assault on Truth. Freud’s Suppression of the Seduction Theory (Boston: Faber and Faber, 1984). Masson also discusses and translates a variety of documents concerning psychiatric abuses, often of a sexual nature, in A Dark Science: Women, Sexuality and Psychiatry in the Nineteenth Century (New York: Farrar, Straus and Giroux, 1986).

13. Peachey was the first to point out to me the literature confirming that battered women looked “schizophrenic” on clinical evaluation and psychological testing. See chapter 2.

Chapter 15

 1.  Cited by Matthew Dumont, “In Bed Together at the Market: Psychiatry and the Pharmaceutical Industry,” American Journal of Orthopsychiatry 60 (1990): 484–85.

 2.  “APA Official Actions,” American Journal of Psychiatry 147 (1990): 1401.

 3.  “Alprazolam First Drug to Receive FDA Approval for Treatment of Panic Disorder,” Psychiatric News, January 4, 1991.

 4.  American Journal of Psychiatry 138 (October 1981): 1408.

 5.  Tina Adler, “Budget Deal Is Sweet to Behavioral Science,” APA Monitor (American Psychological Association) 21 (December 1990): 1. The report says that NIMH has “almost reached sacred-cow status” in Congress, an enormous tribute to the mental health lobby, led by the psycho-pharmaceutical complex and joined by the American Psychological Association.

 6.  The figures are taken from the “Report of the Treasurer,” American Journal of Psychiatry 143 (1986): 1340, table 2.

 7.  For criticism of Judd’s focus at NIMH, see Tina Adler, “Judd Leaves NIMH, Returns to Old Job,” APA Monitor 21 (December 1990): 6.

 8.  See “Neuroleptics to Carry FDA Class Warning,” Psychiatric News, May 17, 1985. The FDA warning on tardive dyskinesia, which was hammered out in consultations with the drug companies and organized psychiatry, contains no hint of the extraordinary frequency of the disease (see chapter 4). It states that “prevalence of the syndrome appears to be highest among the elderly,” and while this is true, it leaves room for the wholly misleading conclusion that it is not very high among all drug-treated persons, including children and young adults.

 9.  “Two New Psychiatric Drugs,” FDA Drug Bulletin 20, no. 1 (April 1990): 9.

10. Ibid.

11. The Generic Division of the FDA determines which firms will get into the marketplace with a generic version of a drug when the patent runs out. Charles Chang, an FDA chemist who has pleaded guilty to accepting gifts from the pharmaceutical industry, describes in an affidavit the influence that drug manufactures exert over the FDA. He confesses that “favoritism and special handling of applications were common in the division of generic drugs,” involving high-ranking FDA officials. He describes “continuous pressure put on the division, at all levels, by the [pharmaceutical] industry through lobbying, conducted by executives, lawyers, consultants, and occasionally through political channels inside and outside the FDA.” He found that “the larger and more sophisticated generic firms received special treatment, primarily through personal contacts within the division.”

12. Letter from Lewis Judd, professor and chair, Department of Psychiatry, University of California, San Diego, to Laurie Flynn, executive director, NAMI, November 15, 1990.

13. Rael Jean Isaac and Virginia C. Armat’s book, Madness in the Streets: How Psychiatry and the Law Abandoned the Mentally Ill (New York: Free Press, 1990), reflects the view of NAMI’s leadership. The dust jacket carries endorsements from the past president of NAMI and the current president of the California branch, CAMI. The acknowledgments thank “above all” a CAMI representative. The book supports lobotomy, electroshock, drugs, more severe forms of involuntary treatment, and state mental hospitals. It attacks the patients’ rights movement and critics of biopsychiatry.

14. Milt Freudenheim, “Maker of Schizophrenia Drug Bows to Pressure to Cut Cost,” New York Times, December 6, 1990. While the reduced cost of the drug is hailed as a humanitarian outcome, it really means that many more patients will be forced to take a drug that produces a particularly overwhelming lobotomy effect (see chapters 3 and 4).

15. The 1987 GAP report laments that the competition is encroaching on psychiatry: “As a growing number of mental health specialists and other physicians become eligible for third-party reimbursements and the competition for patients increases, it becomes vital for the public to understand the role of psychiatrists” (p. 16). The psychiatrist’s claim to the lion’s share of the market lies in his medical identity—his or her “special skills in the diagnosis and treatment of mental disorders.” If these disorders are not genetic and biological, then psychologists and other nonmedical professionals could just as well do the diagnosing and treating. In fact, they often provide better services.

Chapter 16

 1.  The problem with quoting Jung and Freud, as well as many other famous therapists, is that they also had so many horrendous things to say. In Civilization and Its Discontents (1930) (trans. James Strachey [New York: W. W. Norton, 1962], 57), Freud called the ethical rule “Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself “this grandiose commandment.” In a footnote he quotes Heine: “One must, it is true, forgive one’s enemies—but not before they have been hanged.”

 2.  Carter Umbarger, Andrew Morrison, James Dalsimer, and Peter Breggin, College Students in a Mental Hospital: An Account of Organized Social Contacts Between College Volunteers and Mental Patients in a Hospital Community (New York: Grune and Stratton, 1962). Also see Peter Breggin, “The College Student and the Mental Patient,” in College Student Companion Program: Contribution to the Social Rehabilitation of the Mentally Ill (Connecticut State Department of Mental Health and NIMH, 1962).

 3.  See, for example, Roger Coate and Jerel Rosati, eds., The Power of Human Needs in World Society (Boulder, Colo.: Lynne Rienner, 1984); and John Burton, Conflict Resolution and Provention (New York: St. Martin’s Press, 1990). I am currently working on a book based on similar principles: Peter Breggin, Beyond Conflict (tentative) (New York: St. Martin’s Press, forthcoming). I believe love is the most thorough method of conflict resolution.

 4.  The quotations from Pinel and Esquirol are in Thorn Shipley, ed., Classics in Psychology (New York: Philosophical Library, 1961).

 5.  How badly hospitals have treated patients over the past one hundred years is documented in many sources, including Emil Kraepelin, One Hundred Years of Psychiatry (New York: Philosophical Library, 1962); and Albert Deutsch, The Mentally Ill in America, 2d ed. (New York: Columbia University Press, 1949). That the gross mistreatment continues is documented in the Joint Hearings of the Subcommittee on the Handicapped of the Committee on Labor and Human Resources, Care of Institutionalized Mentally Disabled Persons, pts. 1 and 2, April 1–3, 1985 (Washington, D.C.: Government Printing Office).

 6.  See Loren Mosher and Lorenzo Burti, Community Mental Health: Principles and Practices (New York: W. W. Norton, 1989); Loren Mosher, Ann Reifman, and Alma Menn, “Characteristics of Nonprofessionals Serving as Primary Therapists for Acute Schizophrenics,” Hospital and Community Psychiatry 24 (1973): 391—96; Loren Mosher and Alma Menn, “Community Residential Treatment for Schizophrenia: A Two-Year Follow-up,” Hospital and Community Psychiatry 29 (1978): 715–23; Susan Matthews et al., “A Non-Neuroleptic Treatment for Schizophrenia: Analysis of the Two-Year Postdischarge Risk of Relapse,” Schizophrenia Bulletin 5 (1979): 322–33; and Loren Mosher et al., “Milieu Therapy in the 1980s: A Comparison of Two Residential Alternatives to Hospitalization,” Bulletin of the Menninger Clinic 50 (May 1986): 229–322.

 7.  In addition to the studies on family communication cited in this section, several are contained in an excellent compendium: Thomas W. Miller, ed., Stressful Life Events (Madison, Conn.: International Universities Press, 1989). It also cites research indicating that so-called schizophrenia can be caused by stress. See chapters 2 and 5 for further discussion of these issues.

 8.  The national office of the Association for Humanistic Psychology is in San Francisco. The annual conferences, as well as regional meetings, are held in a variety of places around the country.

 9.  Re-evaluation Co-counseling, Fundamentals of Co-Counseling Manual (Seattle: Rational Island, 1962). (Rational Island Publishers, P.O. Box 2081, Main Office Station, Seattle, Washington 98111.) The principles draw on a specific approach to psychotherapy, and the individuals who help each other through these techniques are, by almost any definition, “doing psychotherapy,” although they may not be getting paid for it.

Acknowledgments

This book is the culmination of a lifetime of scientific, educational, and reform work and therefore draws insights, information, inspiration, and sustenance from many different people.

Most important is my wife, Ginger Ross-Breggin, who guided me, in the most gentle fashion, toward finding a more popular style of writing about complex technical subjects and helped edit the entire manuscript. She developed the filing system required for such a mammoth endeavor and carried on myriad back-up tasks over the years. She helped discover relevant research materials and often contributed directly to my grasp of the subjects. Yet her most important contribution cannot be described so simply. It has more to do with how she lives—with love and concern for all expressions of life and for the earth itself. She keeps me better connected to both the details and the essence of life. Our mutual feeling that there is an equal exchange between us is a blessing. During this time, Ginger also has been going to school, developing her artistic talents, delivering papers, coauthoring a book with me on conflict resolution, and being a mother to our children.

The influence of Leonard Roy Frank permeates the book. Himself the victim of electroshock and insulin coma when he was a young man, he has gone on to become a leader in psychiatric reform through his educational, organizational, and literary efforts. A constant stream of relevant books and articles has flowed across the continent from Leonard’s library and files to mine. He, too, read and helped to edit the entire manuscript and, next to my wife, provided the most important input. His generosity and spiritual verve have been a constant source of encouragement. Leonard is now compiling a book of quotations, from which most of the quotations at the chapter headings of this book are drawn.

Pam Clay, an outstanding patient rights attorney, embodying the best traditions of law, has made a significant impact on the care of inmates in her state of Kentucky. She read the entire manuscript and made many valuable comments; but her main contribution has been in the regular sharing of her enormous enthusiasm and intelligence, and her inspiring devotion to the rights and well-being of those too powerless to protect themselves.

In addition to Ginger, Leonard, and Pam, several other people have read some or all of the manuscript, as well as giving me other reasons to be grateful to them. Rae Unzicker, national coordinator of the National Association of Psychiatric Survivors (NAPS), triumphed over years of psychiatric abuse to become an outstanding leader in psychiatric reform. She has regularly bestowed her extraordinary warmth on me. Jeffrey Moussaieff Masson became the first psychoanalyst to defrock himself rather than promote the self-serving cultishness of the psychoanalytic establishment. As someone who has stood up for principle at great personal cost to himself, Jeffrey has been able to provide me extra infusions of moral support and courage. He also provided important materials for the book. Another brave individual, neurologist John Friedberg, became the first physician to stand up effectively in public against electroshock, and he belongs in the medical hall of fame for bravery. He has helped educate me over the years. Robert Morgan and Bertram Karon, psychologists and authors, have persistently told the truth about psychiatric fictions in their own writings and have lent me their support. A psychologist, writer, and former president of the American Academy of Psychotherapists (AAP), Larry Tirnauer has been a regular confidant through the ups and downs of my reform efforts, often adding needed balance to my critiques. As an author, Kate Millett inspired me to reexamine my attitudes on feminist issues in the early 1970s, and more recently she has become a friend and coworker on behalf of patient rights. Psychiatrist Eileen Walkenstein, another source of personal support, has written several books critical of biopsychiatric dogma and practice and promoting a more caring, mutual approach to patients. Psychiatrist Gerald Dubin has been for many years an unfailing friend and supporter and, before he retired from psychiatry, a model of kindness and gentleness as a psychotherapist. Neurologist Robert Grimm, M.D., a marvelous physician, long-standing friend and moral support, made useful contributions to the editing, as did sociologist Phil Brown, Ph.D., and professor of social work David Cohen, Ph.D.

Over the years of reform work, I’ve also had useful input, help, and moral support from many other people to whom I want to express my gratitude, including psychiatrists Loren Mosher, Giovanni de Girolamo, David Richman, and Robert Seidenberg; social psychiatrist Ruth Peachey; educator Marshall Fritz; audiovisual specialist James Turney; patient advocates Bill Johnson and Mary Olympia, who are mainstays of the National Association of Rights Protection and Advocacy (NARPA); the entire board of directors of NARPA, including Paul Freddolino and Renee Bostick; physicians Lawrence Plumlee, Jay Salwen, and Lars Martensson; psychologists Les Ansel, David Hill, Seth Farber, and Judi Striano; mediation counselor Ingrid Kepler-May; social worker Michael Weinberg; filmmaker Beverly Jones; Ira Gruber and Sonja Kjaer of the Tardive Dyskinesia/Tardive Dystonia National Association; and Helen Geis, the parent of a psychosurgery victim. I also want to thank Diana James, assistant to Gloria Steinem, for offering moral support as I have increasingly confronted the issues of male supremacy in psychiatry and society.

Many other people, too numerous to mention, have mailed me a constant stream of news clippings and other materials from around the world, and I want to thank them and to ask them to keep it up.

Many members of the psychiatric survivor movement were interviewed for the book or otherwise contributed through conversations, correspondence, published writings, or organizational activities. Beyond those already mentioned, I want to thank Don Weitz, Irit Shimrat, Sally Zinman, Jenny Miller, Sandra Everett, Marilyn Rice, Fancher Bennett, John Basham, Ron Thompson, Linda Andre, Jay Mahler, Susan Witte, Howie the Harp, Janet Foner, Janet Gotkin, Lynda Wright, Huey Freeman, George Ebert, Mary Ann Ebert,[*] Paul Dorfner, Dayna Caron, Peter Lehmann, Karl Jensen, Lise Smedal, Caia Garupi, Maths Jespersen, and activist attorneys Jean Matulis, Ted Chabasinski, and Carla McKague. Among the survivors, I especially want to acknowledge David Oaks, who gives voice to the movement through his journal, Dendron; Alice M. Earl for the special reports she publishes in her Peer Advocate; Judi Chamberlin, who contributes in so many ways with her keen insights and hard work on behalf of patient rights and survivor-run alternatives; and Dennis Nester, who has made it a personal crusade to publicize the damaging effects of psychiatric treatments. I want to emphasize that I have worked directly with these and many other survivors throughout the world, and have gained immensely from them.

About two dozen of the people I’ve already mentioned are members of the board of directors or advisory council of the Center for the Study of Psychiatry, an educational and reform network of more than seventy-five people that I founded 1971 and have directed ever since. Needless to say, not everyone in such a large group agrees with all of my viewpoints or all of the ideas expressed in this book; but each of them has given his or her moral support to my work. Among those whom I have not yet mentioned, I especially want to thank Congressman Ronald V. Dellums, Congressman Louis Stokes, and Senator Steven Symms, all of whom have been members of the Center for the Study of Psychiatry for two decades, and I want to acknowledge those who work with them on Capitol Hill and have contributed so much to my efforts, including Robert Brauer and Joe Cobb.

Richard Rubenstein, J.D., director of the Institute for Conflict Analysis and Resolution at George Mason University, where I teach, is a more recent member of the Center for the Study of Psychiatry. I am grateful to him and everyone at George Mason for providing me an exciting academic home. Jerry Miller, D.S.W., founder of the National Center for Institutions and Alternatives (NCIA), has provided special direction and support over the years.

Attorney Earl Dudley, Jr., now professor of law at the University of Virginia, has given me invaluable advice, help, and moral support at crucial moments for many years, and has exemplified for me the highest ethical standards of his profession. Ralph Temple, former director of the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) in Washington, D.C., and an outstanding civil rights attorney, guided me successfully through the most hazardous of recent times, helping turn an attack on me into an enormous gain for the reform movement.[1]

Two people who are not members of the Center also have played key roles in backing up my reform work and, closely related, my individual rights. Stuart Comstock-Gay, director of the Maryland ACLU, brought his organization to my support at a critical moment during the recent attack. Hubert “Hank” Schlosberg has been by my side—or only a telephone call away—almost from the very beginning. One of Washington, D.C/s most respected attorneys, Hank first came to my aid in the early 1970s when he virtually donated his time to make sure that my efforts, and even my career, were not quickly snuffed out. The informal defense team of Temple, Schlosberg, and Dudley has proved to be most formidable. I am profoundly grateful to them.

Finally, I want to thank the remaining members of the Center for the Study of Psychiatry, the great majority of whom have gone beyond lending their name to my reform efforts. They include Kenneth Barney, M.D., Ralph Barocas, Ph.D., Melvin Belli, J.D., Linne Bourget, Ph.D., Mark Burrell, Ph.D., Phyllis Chesler, Ph.D., Lee Coleman, M.D., S. Dallas Cooley, M.D., Jonathan Ecker, M.D., C. Timothy Golumbeck, M.D., Jay Haley, Karl Hess, Keith Hoeller, Ph.D., Diane Jayson, Ph.D., Gabe Kaimowitz, J.D., David Keirsey, Ph.D., Robert D. Kephart, the late Arthur Koestler, Ron Leifer, M.D., Kim Long, M.S.W., Cloe Madanes, the late Robert Mendelsohn, M.D., Thomas Nerney, Edward Opton, Jr., Ph.D., J.D., Norman Pearl, M.D., Sharon Presley, Ph.D., Peter Prudden, M.D., Jack Raher, M.D., Kenneth Ruby, M.D., Viktor Sanua, Ph.D., Tim Seldin, M.Ed., Milton Shore, Ph.D., Joyce Shulman, M.S.W., Ph.D., Lee Shulman, Ph.D., Richard Shulman, Ph.D., Marvin Skolnick, M.D., E. Mark Stern, Ed.D., Don Turner, M.D., Emilio Viano, Ph.D., and Robyn Zeiger, Ph.D., who is the current chair of the Center and a loved friend and colleague.

Many attorneys and advocates around the country have worked extensively with me in patients’ rights and malpractice suits, and I have learned a great deal from them. They are literally too numerous to begin naming. I also want to thank the many members of the media who have covered the reform movement and who, on occasion, have stood on principle in defense of my freedom of speech. In regard to that principle, I especially want to thank Oprah Winfrey and her marvelous staff.

Over the years, several wonderful people have helped me as office and research assistants. Carol Valentine helped get the Center on its feet before there was much support in the wider world. Kelly Bangham and Kristen Magruder literally grew up around my office, adding greatly to my enjoyment of the work, and it’s a pleasure to have Krissy back again. Wade Hudson made valuable contributions in helping to research several sections of this book, including psychiatry’s relation to the drug industry. Another research assistant, Patrick Lufkin, helped trace the financial history of the American Psychiatric Association. Ravel Lutz, who was my assistant until recently, contributed to keeping the whole operation going, helped with editing, and made critical forays into the National Library of Medicine. Marilyn Cramer joined us as a word processor and became an editor as well, and finally Claudia DeMino has now become my do-it-all full-time assistant.

I am blessed with a superlative New York agent, Richard Curtis, who understands and supports my work, and doubly blessed with St. Martin’s senior editor, Jared Kieling, who enthusiastically backed this book project. Surely that is more than an author can hope for in one literary lifetime.

Last I want to thank my children, Alysha, Benjamin, Sharon, and Linda. Not only have they shown appreciation for my reform work and my writing efforts, they have graciously accepted the competition for my time. Most recently, they have also patiently endured hours of book-title discussions.

Paradoxically, while I’ve had so much moral support, this book has been largely a private odyssey. Few people who are critical of psychiatric technology and biopsychiatric theories wish to spend a substantial segment of their lives studying them to become expert, nor do they necessarily want to risk the hazards of speaking out in public against them. Most of the people I have thanked in this acknowledgment have given me, above all else, the encouragement needed to proceed with this fundamentally lonely and sometimes hazardous task. Yet the writing of this acknowledgment has served to remind me that loneliness is something I need never complain of again. That is what I most wish to thank my many friends for.

The future of reform in psychiatry rests in large part with the psychiatric survivors themselves and the growing vitality of their movement. The survivors provide mutual support for each other, they educate the public about the dangers of psychiatric treatment and incarceration, and they are developing self-help alternatives that may ultimately supplant much of psychiatry. But like any reform or rights movement, the survivors need support from the rest of us. I want this book to honor and encourage them.[*][†]

____________

*Unlike the others in this list, Mary Ann is not a survivor of psychiatry.

*The Appendixes describe how to get in touch with the psychiatric survivor movement, as well as how to stay abreast of the activities of the Center for the Study of Psychiatry.

†In all cases described in this book, unless both a first and last name are used, identifying details have been omitted or changed to protect confidentiality without affecting the substance of the story.